well to continue where we left off
regarding the
mind so what do we
say well we gave the examples of the the
mind being the animal that needs to be
trained that you paired
with we explained or
described way to look for it which was
most accurately this as in
between in between the internal sense of
the body perception and what's being
felt I think you refer to the space the
space between those when have to see the
two yeah so obviously I think it can
lead people to think like they're going
to see
something in that space in between the
mind will be there but no the space in
between is the mind
so that's as closely as you can Define
it that really helped me actually or it
was very I found it very good because
that was one of the issues I've had with
this word the mind that at least
especially because for a very long time
I was kind of thinking of it as a a
separate entity like that endures almost
like a kind of a projection or it's
almost like another word for self
basically that you just don't want to
itself so you say it's all bundled
together but yeah yeah so it's like so
you're not going to see a separate
phenomenon within that space clarifying
that space means clarifying the
mind so that space in
between is what the animal
is so we talk about taming the animal
means taming the space
between so is that space in between is
it closer than
the body
internally and feeling or is it
father so there's a sense of internal
body physicality right
here being felt is a sense of
feeling on that kind of mental
counterpart simultaneous presence of the
two reveals you the space in between
peripherally from where you are
at is that space closer or
father from these things that
determinate perception and feeling
basically so from the point of view of
establishing the correct mindfulness
neither here y i there I in between
um which is the closest which is
the does the space in between feel
closer or farther than those things they
Define the space in
between
exactly why say closer
why kind of what did you
say would you say that
because you have to see those things for
like it's kind count of seeing those
things that you can find the space in
between which is sort of yeah underneath
not as far not as far from them and
that's what makes you like that's why
you need to see those things first in
order to like discern in between in
between otherwise it would be the other
way around so it's in between the
distance you have to basically attend
mhm so it's always going to be closer
and that's why
it's I mean I was saying that
before it's it's um it's so close that's
the sole reason for being overlooked you
just can't see it exactly cuz you just
like lit like lens in front of your eye
that you have no reference for and you
just see the stuff through the lens so
it's like nothing that points there's
actually a lens there but you don't see
that you couldn't you when you said is
it closer or further than your point of
view then it becomes kind of yeah of
course yeah from the point closer to the
point of view exactly where from which
you would be attending from which you
would be sort of from from the from the
Mano if if you want to be
technical um so yeah and the reason why I'm asking
um so yeah and the reason why I'm asking
that is because well see that's why it's
kind of I don't
of I don't
ically the closest yet the f is because
of that yeah because you just have no
means for seeing that in
between thus the closest thing is
utterly invisible so that's why we go far and
invisible so that's why we go far and
wide due to the pressures of that
closest thing CU you don't really know
where it comes from so you're just
seeking um
um
satisfaction acting out
here and there in regard to this in
regard to that because this is just
invisible this is why I was kind of
chuckling to myself because I was
thinking like it's further away in the
sense that I just I don't have any kind
of concrete thing to even be talking
about with this well I think that's the
in order to be able to talk about it and
see it you need to start redefining your
definition of what concrete
is I think one of the reason people
would't see it is because they expect or
they kind of imply that the only real
things that are seen have to have a
certain level of concreteness to them
but then everything that's less concrete
you just would
Overlook it's similar to how
like most people don't even see thoughts
as real exactly it's exactly the same
principle feelings is well
moods real as such that's what I keep
saying so space in between is real as
such actually it's not an
actually it's not an
abstraction I mean it will be if you if
you don't know it's really such and if
the mind is not developed to see it real
as such that attitude the view behind it
so you're just going to be overlooking it
it
so that animal
that space let's put it broadly between your
space let's put it broadly between your
body and the feeling felt
simultaneously when I say body I don't
mean Sensations I don't mean external
watching of your body or internally
following your Sensations just mean the
sense of the body as a whole whatever
the image you might associate with it
and the feeling so a space in between
the two that
animal well what is that animal
see does it can it see everything you
see does it have
access to the five
senses is there only perception in the
sense that there
are there's perceptions of craving and
there are perceptions of non- craving so
well you could say those are the the
only things it's capable of trained
untrained but what I'm asking
is does it see everything you see as
well is it like like your companion with
whom you
together watch the world and make
decisions in regard to it or is there a
different relationship between you and
the world and animal and you
so if I were to describe the
relationship between me and the world
then it's possible for me to discern
that I am perceiving my sense is
perceiving the world it's possible yeah
okay but for the
animal it is only it is only in
relationship with perception which well
what do you mean with
perception so obviously what I just
described is a percep perception so the
the discernment that I'm perceiving per
I'm perceiving the senses perceiving uh
well see that's that could easily be
just a view you're telling to yourself
you don't necessarily think oh I'm
seeing my senses seeing this you just
see things and generally that's your
things and generally that's your
relationship with the world from here to
Y so animal being neither here nor y
does it see here and Yonder does it see
also these sense objects that you go
after or it seees something entirely
different you trapped a wild
dog you now fenced off with it
together what are you looking at what is
the dog looking at
well is a hint
so
if
your body language I physical actions
verbal language I verbal actions mental
language I mental actions if that is the
sole factor that either agitates or Cals the
factor that either agitates or Cals the
Wild
dog what does the dog see what is he
looking
at it's looking at you that's all it can
see the space in between is not pointed
towards what you're looking past it oh
look at his s s look look all it sees is
you nothing
else that's why you're actually matter
even if you don't think they do they
might not matter to anything else but it
matter to this big black dog that's
staring that all it sees is you cuz
you're the only one tracked with it
there there's nothing else for can't see
past the fence you
can and because of always looking like
because you're used to looking past it
past the past the fence you ignore
ignore the dog and that's why you would
be trying to use like deal with those
things past the
yeah for the sake of but all the mind
can see is you
yeah and that's that the whole mirror
similar to Raa that would
gave like what can mirror see if it's
like in front of you only you that's the
so thing that's going to be reflected
there so that's why the physical the
body language matters the verbal
language matters the not
because some psychologizing factor or
possible outcome or something like that
no it's
because this type of phys body language
means this for the animal that can only
see you and stares at
you so that space in
between does not really see here y
doesn't even know those things
exist all it is is what you
do and he doesn't see why why you're
doing it that's the important but dog
does not
know that big wild dog doesn't know why
doesn't care
why oh he's waving his arm because no it
doesn't matter this type of body
matter this type of body
language aggravates
it the other type of body language calms
it down it doesn't care
why and that becomes your new
why in other words well I won't do this
body language why well because the Wild
dog is getting agitated and I'm the only
one close with
it I shall do this body language oh but
why look everybody else is doing this
well then not everybody else is closed
with this wild do they have their own
and they're going to pay the price if
they don't tame
it so your mental actions the same
principle but obviously the courses is
the physical things that you do or
abstain from doing the verbal things
that you say or abstain from
saying and then yes the the mental
things that you choose to intentionally
revolve around or abstain from doing so
yes the possibilities remain there for
either of those but by not giving into
to them you send the message to the dog
not by not having them there as a
possibility that's never an issue the
issue is well what do I do on account of
this that's like why some of the
principles like why you could like
somebody could abandon the defilements
out of Faith just by like without you
need to like if you stick to that
behavior like if you stick if you stick
to that behavior or un behavior of
establishing virtue you would be
defining the space in between even if
you don't necessarily think in any more
detail that's being established in
virtue basically
and then if you continue in reference to
the space in between in reference to
Chet in reference to the wild
animal continue avoiding unsuitable
sound melt touches they would make you
act unsuitable the animal will calm down so
unsuitable the animal will calm down so
that's you protect your
senses not because of you oh I can
handle it yeah you probably can that's
not the issue but you being exposed to
those S sound smell taste touches of the
unsuitable kind sends a message to the
animal so when you seeing those things
animal sees you seeing those things and
whether you like it or not you look the
certain way for that animal let's say
like that so that's why those sites are
always unsuitable even if you can handle
them because you will look the certain
way and that way would be agitating the
animal generally only an Arun has a full
tamed friendly dog that cannot bite him
under any circumstances even if the
highway robbers are chopping his limbs
off he would not send the wrong message
to that
dog and that's really what
um what anxiety
is just even
colloquially sorry finish what was that
well just like knowing that at any
moment like well not knowing not necessarily
like well not knowing not necessarily
knowing but feeling the proximity of the
dog that can go either way yeah at any
time at any time on account of anything
so that's why the
distractions um
entertainment um well anything the
people do that's rooted in the intention
to distract themselves it's basically
just trying to add things in between you
and the dog so again it can't happen
that's that space cannot increase where
between you and the dog nothing can be
placed in between but you can just
believe that now there's something
between so the dog is not seeing me but
you're also not seeing the dog like by
giving importance too sure sure yeah you
you kind of forget about it but deep
down that is the sole reason for you
needing that distraction so you're
always carrying it with
you um and that's again in the
Solitude not even like solitud more like
non- entertainment really I think that's
like you know what people talk about
Solitude L people want to practice five
precepts eight precepts and solitude but
I can't get into Solitude because well I
have no means of it finding a secluded
place you be closer to Solitude by
giving up entertainment than by going
into physical Solitude on your own so
giving up things that you do to distract
yourself from yourself and you're going
to have perfect Solitude or more than
able more than sufficient
Solitude so when you know says that
Solitude is a
prerequisite to see the signs of your
mind ey to see the space in
between you could translate that as
non-entertainment non- distraction of
the sufficient kind is the prerequisite
to
see in between to see and that's why we
had householders back in the day so so
did see the mind sure they were there
with the Buddha talking and he guided
them but
still but of course if you can get into
Solitude meaning no access to the
distracting things it will lead in the
same direction but if you can't get in
solitude but you could still exercise
your restraint and not give into the
distracting thing and that will be your
Solitude and that's why I did see I did
hear people I remember in the past
saying like although it doesn't feel like a big
like although it doesn't feel like a big
deal the the little
entertainments you know I don't know Len
music okay maybe music is a bit too
course but I don't know read the
news yeah read the news just checking
the news it's not a big deal it's not
I'm not spending two hours watching a
movie or something I just read the news
and stuff just giving up those little
things starts filling them with a sense
of panic
just giving up this little you know
touching base here and there with these
little familiarities starts giving you the the
familiarities starts giving you the the
anxiety and oh but I need to do it solit
that's all that's your Solitude there
and then that you're running away
from and you can be surrounded with your
whole crowded noisy family shouting
screaming but when it com comes to your
choice if you're not choosing the
distraction for the sake of distracting
yourself for the sake of magically
believing that this can be placed
between me and the wild animal that's
constantly that that that just
lives for looking at me that's all it
can see that's all it
has then you'll be alone even in such
crowded
environment it's common for people to
think that like if they live in a
crowded environment there like no point really
environment there like no point really
no point even try yeah yeah exactly in
restraining but no the whole point of
physical seclusion is to take you
establish you in environment of non
little distractions that are done for
the sake
of blurring the space between you and
the mind and see that's exactly why people
mind and see that's exactly why people
would feel
like you know rest um
relax um remove the tension when they
engage with distracting activities which
are actually quite quite
tiring they're not relaxing by any mean
but they're not as tiring as the
knowledge of the Wild dog staring at you
at your every move so it's like I can't
hide from this
so let me engage in these well as I said
activities that obviously imply A
Certain Magical belief that you are now
invisible cuz you stop thinking about it
you know a kid covers its eyes when
something scares it so by covering my
eyes there's no more danger well that's
pretty much exactly the same thing
you're still doing when you're engage
with distraction or I forget about it thus
distraction or I forget about it thus
it's not there anymore yet it remains as
close and even more agitated now
so that's why that would feel
relaxing cuz you feel like you're not
being
watched and that's why the delusion is
the worst and the hardest to get rid of
you factually feel like you're not being
watched while you're actually still
being watched and sending a very wrong
message and it's again it's not I mean
we spoke about it I think before um in
Sona DEA it was it's not like yeah okay
I got to abandon everything must look at
anything no no no no no those intentions
are probably not even
that many during the day it's not like
every second you're choosing a
distraction but when you do you know it
and that's when you do it and that's
when you shouldn't be doing it yeah you
you get distracted by this by that but
none of that was fully intentional so of
course it's not the most optimal but
it's nowhere near as bad as
if oh no no no I'm choosing this now
because the Panic is setting in because
the Panic is setting in because I I I I
I you know I really need to read the
news and listen and go and see these
people and go watch this or go talk
about this and so on
and that's pretty much the anxiety
when even an ignorant anxiety is when
the circumstances would
circumstances would
have well showed you the de animal is as
close As It Ever
Was that it's still unpredictable you
still cannot trust it that he won't bite
you you're not sure how would you feel
if you just suddenly turn around and
there is a big massive dog Wild next to
your face it might lick my face he might
be a friendly one but he might not so
imagine how you would feel you would
feel exactly how you feel anytime when
you're anxious it's like o this can go out the
anxious it's like o this can go out the
way but see for those who don't even see
the mind they don't even they feel it
cuz the animals there the mind is
felt and there's an extra lay to it on
account of like not even know where from
like everything and nothing and just
that complete Panic then sets in yeah
but the point is
um no no I was just going to say like
you can say like oh yes so you don't
know how things will turn out so you're
anxious but you're not really anxious
because of that there is another layer
in between that's more direct cause for
a anxiousness and that's that mind that
you don't trust or it doesn't trust you
right both both ways so you don't know
how things will turn out means animal
could act on account of things turning
out this or that way it can act either
way and that's what you
feel not how circumstances will
circumstances cannot cause you the
anxiety cannot cause you
anything that's exactly like say if you
would have tamed your mind completely
that you have not a grain of doubt in
your mind that it cannot possibly bite
you even if somebody's stabbing it with
Spears it will not bite
you then you have no fear in regard to
circumstances even if it's highers
chopping your limbs because it never
came from
that let's give it let's take the
example of what you said somebody out of
Faith doing this rightly what would what
would they be doing rightly give me a
few examples so that the
examples so that the
wildo that's infinitely
close cannot be any anywhere else cannot
look at anything else except you and
your behavior so that that dog can be tained
behavior so that that dog can be tained
and eventually fully trusted that you
can not turn against
you what would they be doing out of
faith rightly that would result in
calming of the dog rightly
stop as broadly as you want you're not
resisting any painful feeling you know
because as you're doing
that and I'm just thinking about the
mind of friendl that's the mind of
friendliness because of my
non-resistance let's start a bit broader
that's true but that would come a bit
later why would you do first and
foremost well
restraint keeping the precepts not
acting out acting out not acting out
like when there's pressure not acting
out of that
pressure let's say pressure for un
wholesome for un wholesome that CU that
makes you kind of know like you know
when things are yeah lying cheating
stealing stealing
killing um misbehavior anger bad speed
things that are consciously
intentionally done that have no reason to be done
done that have no reason to be done
basically except any kind ofers pleasure
you might be getting from
it so
restraining keeping the precepts setting
up
that
container then you could on a more
immediate basis like okay I will also
pay attention to what I choose to look
at listen talk about even if it's within
the precepts well it's not against the
precepts well it's not against the
precepts but I know here and now it's
rooted in distraction or Satler lust or
Satler aversion so I will abstain from
doing that so out of Faith somebody can
do all that
rightly and then exactly then it would
come down to
the Views that you hold
mhm do you want to get rid of the
pressure which sends the message to the
animal you hate it as much as it hates
you yeah or maybe it didn't even hate you
yeah or maybe it didn't even hate you
that much but now it hates you cuz all
you're doing is trying to kill it as far
as it's concerned you want to get rid of
the
pressure that's what I was kind of
thinking was just along a general answer
to your question
was you would have
to let yourself feel the anxiety of
with that dog which means you'd have to
kind of recognize it for what it is well
you don't have to seek it very far you
just have to stop covering it up
actively right like it's not like you
don't you don't even need to uncover it
I got to make this work to dig it up you
just need to stop actively buing it and
it's going to be there one way or the
other and that's exactly anxiety be the
first thing that when people start
keeping the precepts Giving Up
Entertainment and so on is just going to
be that sense of anxiety and panic and
vacuum internally and and it's like well
there you go you're already outlining
your mind right there and
then so but changing the views yeah so
not trying to get rid of the pressure
not learning how not to resist it
despite you know the very strong habit
yeah but if I can only just just just
just just get rid of this just deal with
this then I'll be fine it's like that
that basically sends the wrong
communication to the animal that is
agitating it further
which means he going to pressure you
even
further so what
else so out of Faith you're keeping the
precepts sens Str you're not giving into
the distraction which becomes your
virtual Solitude Solitude eye between you and
Solitude Solitude eye between you and
your mind nothing else being thrown in
between to to to cover
up um not trying to get rid of the
pressure
not blaming other things for
it what else try to deal with other
things so as to not so so this doesn't
come up
yet what else can person be doing out of
Faith along the right lines
so body is restrained speech is
restrained the views have been um
upgraded there's the attitude of
non-resistance in regard to the pressure
you not just automatically trying to
psychologize it justify it remove it
replace it what else can you do out of Faith
it what else can you do out of Faith
there without needing to know a lot
more well like say you're doing all this
right so what else would be there that
hasn't been really that could be
addressed a bit better
now say it thoughts
yes yes the dages exactly you could okay
I I do have a say in what I choose to
revolve around like images present
themselves in the same sense
possibilities for physical actions or
verbal action presenting themselves but
then you choose to engage and
revolve feed and cultivate so it's like
okay so I will not then
uh feed the unsuitable images that are
rooted in lust or anger or cruelty you
know other Su to say or then later
conceit belonging to a clan and so on
those the subtler ones I just want feed
them I will not give give give more
momentum to them when they present
themselves I'm not blaming them for the
problem I am unresisting the pressure
but I could also not just habitually not
give them attention give them yeah give
them unsuitable attention basically
exactly Center Stage Center Stage you
said before yeah don't allow them to
Center Stage let them be there but don't
allow them to Center
Stage what else can you do then out of
faith that can Dain the animal even
further presented with certain
images yeah exactly start start
basically inducing certain context for
it because you know okay it sees me well
let me think about these things of this
kind so that it will reflect back onto
that animal there perceptions
perceptions yeah the perceptions of an
unability um
um
nonresistance the perceptions of
non-resistance that would then establish
the animal in the state of meta
basically as we said before it's the animal that
as we said before it's the animal that
practices meta not you you're just
setting it up for it mind you it's the
animal that practices samadi not you
it's ch is not it's not your thing that
you're doing so that's how you unifying
the animal as well yeah well I'm doing
this no no you can only be setting it up
rightly through the indirect means
through mindfulness correctly
peripherally Discerning stuff so that
then the animal is Unified
elevated what else could you be out of
Faith then so present it with suitable
contexts right
contemplations on the basis of
non-resistance on the basis of virtual
Solitude on the basis of uninterrupted
virtue and
restraint what else can you
do can you talk to directly
now since there is nothing else in
between obscuring the
communication can you tell it to come
down it's
educated you can you always could it's
just that you didn't listen before he
wasn't taking it seriously
enough but now that you would have
purified your body language verbal
language mental language that this
animal is
reading now it's just solely focused
onto you and now when you tell it it
actually hears
you and then you tell it to calm
down you tell it to relinquish you tell
it to let go any
will so is there anything else that the
person on the faith would need to do I'd
say not much
well it's like um depends I mean we
already said present it with certain
contexts that would be on the level of
like um caling it further or unifying it but
um caling it further or unifying it but
then there's also like you were saying I
think one or two talks
ago like presenting it with the like
with the wild elephant you would sort of
show it the the spears or show it the
the the things that like when would you
do that I I don't think we specify that
back then so like just now we described like
then so like just now we described like
this
gradual training
training
uh when would
you know to present the agitating context or
know to present the agitating context or
possibly agitating context to see if
there is agitation in the animal or
presented the non- agitating context
that what what would be
the criteria for that well let's say one
obvious one is if it's agitated already
then you don't need to present a bit
more how do you know it's agitated
already it how are you measuring animals agitation suffering suffering
suffering suffering
acting out acting out pressure being
press
pressure your emotional
outbursts no this would be like way too
Co now for this all of those pretty
much um subtler subtler than all of
that it's kind of where the pressure is
but it's always some pressure I suppose
it's not necessarily going to be
what what what do you do in regard to
pressure what's the first thing you do
in regard to pressure what did you say
you should stop doing resistance resist
yeah so if there is
resistance if if it's not sufficiently
unresisted then then you shouldn't be
agitating it cuz you're just going to
tighten the resistance so that's why you
first have to unresisted degree of
perceived felt experienced resistance
yeah I guess there yeah there has to be
like also I mean the other possible
answer I suppose could be like when you
know that now you can kind of talk to it
directly because there has to be kind of
a degree of confidence
that you know you can tell it to calm
down you show it something it might
start to get agitated and it will can C
down down yeah that's that's why the
importance of gradual not like people
just hearing the the end parts of the
gradual training and then just trying to
apply that right now so I can get
quicker there it's like you have no
criteria for whether the animal is being
agitated or not you're just throwing
these things that can obviously make it
worse um but see the whole point is like
it will constrict to some extent when
you present it with things that doesn't
want to see so you want to UNC constrict
it first so constrict back is just still
on the neutral
level but if it's already constricted I
there's some resistance
there um presenting with more is just
not going to be
balanced and that's why even when the
Buddha was
teaching first time people they would
come he would always talk first about
benefits you know of
virtue Heavens rebirth great rewards all
of that which kind of oh wow you know
great and it UNC constricts more and
more and more and then he tells them
about the Peril degradation of
sensuality and and so on impermanence
and all of that so there's immediate
constriction but their starting point
has been widened so to speak so when
they constrict back they're going to
constrict onto the middle not too
narrow obviously you know the Buddha
could see that clearly in regard to the
others but you could safely know
that if there is resistance and now
you're presenting these um agitating
context of impermanence mindfulness of
death um discusted and all of that to
the mind without unresisted at first
it's probably going to be rooted in
resistance you're trying to get rid of
it by feeding this to go away quicker to
stop doing it so it's like you're trying
to train a dog with frustration
yeah you're still saying the same things
doing the same thing but your attitude
is
frustrated it's like Oh no I got to stop
that first def frustrate myself UNF
frustrate myself and then do the same
things and I will get very different
message in those two externally same
looking
examples now you could see then all
those simul in the suit test says okay
his work is done
training is
completed the elephant is completely
immovable in the battle or non battle
doesn't matter so the the wild do is
completely T now cannot possibly bite
you under any
circumstance and you fully know
that because you would presented in with
scenarios through the contemplation the
inevitabilities that
used to cause agitation and threat and
anxiety but now it's none of that it's
simply immovable and it looks looks at
you with the same friendly eyes so to
speak and you know
it and you know that you know like you
get a wild crazy dog you tame it you
train it and it's like you know like oh
that dog would give its life for me
basically there's there's nothing that
that that can that can come in between
in that sense well it's exactly the same
for the m
if it's sted so then yeah arand can
literally go in any direction he pleases
towards any
circumstances and he will be completely
unbothered because the root of the
bother was the animal that's now
incapable of that incapable of cing